Well, it's the grand finale.
Now it's time to finish what we started.
This is the final phase of development.
It's where we look through all our code, test our game a bunch of times, make sure everything is perfect
before launch.
But first things first, we have a problem when we click start, which is how all these sprites don't
disappear.
So let's just fix this one by one.
Firstly, with our start button, all we need to do is drag in the when I receive block, change it
to start game and then drag in a hide block.
Then drag a show onto the when flag clicked.
Right.
Testing this out and clicking start, we can see that it works.
Now moving on to our tree sprite.
And this is where we made a mistake previously when we dragged this show block onto our when I receive
start game block.
Actually we don't need this as this happens automatically in our other script so we can just remove
it.
Now we can literally do the same for the other sprites.
Firstly our snow pixel just remove the show.
Then the second snow pixel do the same.
And lastly, with our score, we can also remove the show.
So clicking play, then hitting start.
As you can see, our problem has been fixed.
Now there is one more animation I want to add into our start screen and it is for our start button.
Here I want the button to zoom in and out.
It's basically going to be very similar code to our tree sprite.
So moving over to it we can just drag a when flag clicked a forever to repeat blocks.
And to change size by blocks, which we can stick into each of these.
So for the first one we can set it to 0.2 and the last two -0.2.
And the last thing we need to do is set the size to its current size, which is 25, and then just bring
in a go to block to ensure that it stays in position.
And that's all.
So hitting play as you can see we have a nice little animation and clicking start.
Well that works well.
Now one extra thing that can be improved is our obstacle trees.
If you have played the game for long enough, you can see the trees just kind of appear in a line formation
which which doesn't look very natural.
So moving over to our tree sprite, all you have to do is duplicate this script here, like so.
But now if we had to play it, these trees would spawn at the exact same time, which would be even
more unnatural.
So we want some variability.
To fix this.
We need to use a bit of math.
And I know how much you love your math.
What we can do is remove this variable here and then move over to the operators and grab a few blocks
here, which are this plus a pick random a times block and a divide block.
Then we can duplicate our spawn variable two times.
Now that we have all the pieces, we need to connect them.
So spawn rate plus pick random.
Then the times block into the first input.
Then insert this divide block into this input, and then the spawn variables into each of these inputs.
Now, with all that connected for the first input, we can type two and negative one for the second.
So let's quickly run through this so you understand what we're doing here.
When the game starts we continuously create clones.
Now to make the cloning feel more natural.
And instead of always waiting the same amount of time between clones, we add some randomness.
We determine the waiting time as follows.
Firstly, take the set spawn rate example 0.5 seconds.
Secondly, randomly pick a value between half of the spawn rate subtracted from itself, making it negative
and the full spawn rate.
And thirdly, add this random value to the spawn rate.
So for example, if the spawn rate is 0.5, the waiting time can be anywhere between 0.25 and 0.5 seconds.
The random variation ensures the clones don't appear too predictably, and it gives it a far more natural
feel.
However, the only thing we may need to adjust now is our spawn speed, because now we have two sets
of obstacles.
So to do this, we can lower the initial spawn rate by increasing this number here or changing how much
it decreases over here.
Now there is one other issue you may have picked up on.
If you remove this weight statement, you'll see how sometimes trees appear in front of each other.
How do we fix this?
All we need to do is grab a go to layer block and a move layer block.
Then under the script here, when I start as a clone, we wanted to go to back a layer and then come
forward say 35 layers.
Doing this ensures that our trees are laid correctly, and also that our player is behind our tree so
we can test it out.
And if you have a keen eye, you will notice that the trees are stacked correctly.
And also our player slides behind our trees.
So at this stage, we have reached a very important moment.
Follow along with us.
Really do.
You've got to follow along with this.
Just take a moment.
Put one of your arms up into the air.
Come on, make sure you're doing it.
Put one arm up into the air.
Now reach down as far as you can behind you doing that?
Good.
Now tap somewhere on the middle of your back.
Excellent.
You've just stretched.
But more importantly, you have given yourself a well-deserved pat on the back.
Well done.
Your game is complete, and making it this far means you are one of our top students, and it shows
that you have the persistence of a real programmer.
So well done!
You've done really well to get you, and I think it's time that you sit back, relax and enjoy what
you've created.
Why don't you challenge your friends and family to play your game?
And hey, if you're going to add a secret mechanic that makes the game harder when they played, who
am I to judge your game?
It's your persistence and perseverance that have got you here.
Fantastic job and well done.